Finding Aid for Albert Joseph Engel Jr. papers, 1944-1946 and 1971-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Albert Joseph Engel Jr. papers 1944-1946, 1971-2002
Engel, Albert Joseph, 1924-
16 linear feet
0265 Aa 2
Attorney; judge of the 14th Judicial Circuit of Michigan (1967-1970); United States District Judge for the Western District of Michigan (1971-1973); judge of the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit (1974-2002). Case files, administrative files, and subject files relating to his judicial and other professional responsibilities; also memoirs of his career and letters written while serving in the military during World War II.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Judge Engel (donor no. 4690 ) and came to the library in 2002; additions were received in 2006.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Judge Albert J. Engel was born in Lake City, Michigan, on March 21, 1924, the son of the late Congressman and Mrs. Albert J. Engel.
He was educated in the public schools, Lake City and Washington, D.C. At the conclusion of his sophomore year at the University of Michigan, he entered the United States Army as a private in January, 1943. He left the service in April, 1946 as a captain and commanding officer of a bomb disposal unit. He served in this capacity in Europe with the Ninth Air Force for two years and saw duty in England, France, Belgium and Germany, earning five battle stars. Returning to the University of Michigan, he received an A.B. in 1948 and a J.D. from the University of Michigan Law School in 1950.
Judge Engel was admitted to practice in 1950. After one year as administrative assistant to Representative Ruth Thompson, he returned to Michigan and entered into the private practice of law in the firm of Engel and Engel in Muskegon, Michigan. In 1966 he was elected Judge of the 14th Judicial Circuit of Michigan, taking office January 1, 1967. In 1970, he was appointed United States District Judge for the Western District of Michigan, taking office in January, 1971. He was appointed to the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit in December, 1973, and was sworn in on January 4, 1974, succeeding the late W. Wallace Kent. Judge Engel retired from this position early in 2002.
Judge Engel was a member of the American Bar Association, State Bar of Michigan, Muskegon County Bar Association, Grand Rapids Bar Association, Cincinnati Bar Association, the Federal Bar Association, Chapters in Washington, D.C., Detroit and Grand Rapids, and the American Judicature Society. He was also a Fellow of the American Bar Foundation.
The Albert J. Engel papers consist of case files, miscellaneous administrative files, and subject files relating to his judicial and other professional responsibilities as a judge of the U.S. District Court for the Western District of Michigan (1971-1974) and as a judge on the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit (1974-2002). Case files for each court make up the bulk of the collection. The files represent a selection based largely upon the importance of the issue or issues represented within the case, the significance of the case in the judgment of Judge Engel, and whether Judge Engel wrote the opinion, dissent, or concurrence. Important to understanding the cases are individual memoranda written by Judge Engel (and included in box 15) of his assessment of the cases that he heard.
In 2006, the library received Judge Engel's memoirs of his life and career together with photocopies of the letters that he wrote home during the Second World War, 1944-1945.
Subjects:
Engel, Albert Joseph, 1924-; Judges--United States.; Judges--Michigan.; Law.; World War, 1939-1945--Personal narratives, American.; United States. Court of Appeals (6th Circuit); United States. District Court (Michigan: Western District)
- U.S. Court Of Appeals Case Files
  This series is a selection of U.S. Court of Appeals case files. Judge Engel wrote either the opinion, concurrence or dissent. The notebook containing Judge Engel's memoranda on these and other cases is located in box 15
  - In the Matter of the Complaint of Cambria Steamship Co., Case No. 73-1349/1350. April 3, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Carolyn Ann King, by Gerald E. King, her next friend, Ypsilanti Community American Little League, and the city of Ypsilanti v. Little League Baseball, Inc. Case No. 73-1940. April 17, 1974 (Box 1)
  - U.S. v. Mayes, et. al.; Cook; Fowler; Crawley; and Newberry. Case No. 73-1988/89/90/91/92. February 14, 1974, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Henry Clay Burks v. Charles Egeler, Warden, People of the State of Michigan. Case No. 73-2003. April 16, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Clemens R. Sierakowski v. Caspar Weinberger, Secretary of Health, Education and Welfare. Case No. 73-2054. April 10, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Thor C. Laugesen v. the Anaconda Company. Case No. 73-2205. April 16, 1964 (Box 1)
  - In the Matter of: Erie Lackawanna Railway Co., Debtor. Case No. 74-1192-1195. (Box 1)
  - Fruehauf Corporation, William E. Grace and Robert D. Rowan v. Internal Revenue Service. Case No. 74-1474. October 3, 1974 and on remand, June 16, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Nancy Noe, By Her Guardian Ad Litem v. Laurel True, Secretary, Department for Human Resources, et. al. Case No. 74-1577. October 4, 1974 (Box 1)
  - William Whitten v. Anchor Motor Freight, Inc., et al. Case No. 74-1815. December 2, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Jerry D. Fridrich, et al. v. J.C. Bradford, et al. Case No. 74-1902. February 13, 1975, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - United States of America v. Hal Clemit Derrick and Burnett Wendell Finchum (a/k/a In Re: Derrick) Case No. 74-1923-1924. December 6, 1974 (Box 2)
  - James Jonathon Mapp, et al. v. The Board of Education of the City of Chattanooga, Tennessee, et al. Case No. 74-2100/2101. (Box 2)
  - United States of America v. James Allen Blanton, Jr. Case No. 74-2113. April 17, 1975 (Box 2)
  - United States v. Ford Motor Co., Robert Maier, et. al. Case No. 74-2128. February 3, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Robert C. Bannert v. American Car Company. Case No. 74-2365. April 16, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Shirley v. Chagrin Falls Exempted Village Schools Board of Education, et. al. Case No. 75-1180. April 23, 1975 (Box 2)
  - United States of America v. Jimmie Truitt, Jr. Case No. 75-1188. June 11, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Sylvia Scott Whitlow v. F.E. Hodges, et. al. Case No. 75-1519 September 30, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Security & Exchange Commission v. The Senex Corporation, et. al., and A.J. Jolly and the Mentor Corp., Case No. 75-1656. December 12, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Ramsey, Alexander & Robert F. Newman, et. al. v. Aero Lodge No. 735, Int'l Assoc. of Machinists and Aerospace Workers, AFL-CIO and Avco Corporation, Aerospace Structures Division. Case No. 75-1776/75-2097/2098/2099. October 13, 1976 (Box 2)
  - EEOC v. The New York Times Broadcasting Service, Inc., d/b/a. WREC-TV. Case No. 75-2055. April 6, 1976 (Box 2)
  - United States v. Ronald Grunsfeld, et. al. Case No. 75-2354/2355/2356/2357/2358/2359/2360/2361. June 9, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Ford Motor Company v. United States Environmental Protection Agency and State of Michigan. Case No. 76-1463. June 21, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Terry Drayton, a minor, by her mother and next friend Bernice Drayton, and Bernice Drayton v. Jiffee Chemical Corporation. Case No. 76-1941/1942. December 7, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Barrier v. Egeler, Warden. Case No. 77-1100. October 13, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Joan Woodruff, et. al. v. Hewitt P. Tomlin, Jr. et. al. Case No. 77-1216. October 4, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Arco Industries Corp. v. Chemcast Corp. et. al. Case No. 77-1501. November 28, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Lawrence Roth et. al. v. Bank of the Commonwealth. Case No: 77-1539. December 9, 1977 (Box 3)
  - John E. Haycroft et. al. v. Board of Education of Jefferson County, Kentucky, et. al. Case No: 77-3263. June 13, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Arnold R. Jago v. United States District Court. Case No: 77-3333. October 7, 1977 (Box 3)
  - Utility Workers Union of America, et. al. v. Consumers Power Company and Pension Plan for Employees of Consumers Power Company. Case No. 78-1402. June 22, 1979 (Box 3)
  - United States v. Giacalone, Case No: 78-5055 June 19, 1978 (Box 3)
  - United States v. Carl Sutton, Jr., et. al. Case No: 78-5134/5135 5136/5137/5138/5139//5141/5142/5143. December 1, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Noah Harrison Lundy v. Vinson Thompson, Warden and the Attorney General of Tennessee. Case No. 79-1280. June 16, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Waller Brothers Stone Co. v. United Steelworkers of America, et. al. Case No: 79-3254. October 2, 1979 (Box 3)
  - The Cleveland-Cliffs Iron Company and Burlington Northern, Inc. v. Interstate Commerce Commission and the U.S. of A. Case No. 79-3775/3777/80-3020/3159/3161. October 21, 1980, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - United States v. Ronald Morelli, Case No: 79-5031. March 31, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Albert J. Doherty v. American Motors Corp. Case No: 80-1655. November 8, 1982 (Box 3)
  - The Hanna Mining Company. A Delaware Corporation v. the Escanaba and Lake Superior Railroad Company, A Michigan Corporation. Case. No: 80-1681. February 5, 1981 (Box 3)
  - Beverly Hills Fire Litigation. Case No: 80-3320/3358/3359/3360. July 9, 1981, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Madeline Marie Nursing Homes. Case No. 80-3549. October 20, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Sovereign News Company v. Lee Falke and Roy Warner, et al. / William Lee v. Cleveland Municipal Court, Frank G.O'Bill and William J. Brown. Case No: 80-3694/80-3696/3728/3742/3743/3817/81-3127. October 7, 1981, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Wayne Boich d/b/a W.B. Coal Co. v. Federal Mine Safety and Health Review Commission, et.al. Case No: 81-3186 May 27, 1982 (Box 4)
  - Mobil v. Marathon. Case No. 81-3704/3711/3713. December 17, 1981, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - United States v. James M. Allen, Leonard Ray Blanton, and Clyde Edward Hood, Jr. Case No: 81-5643/5644/5645. June 20, 1983, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Irma Howard v. Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, et. al. Case No: 82-1960. January 27, 1984 (Box 4)
  - Air Pollution Control District of Jefferson County, Kentucky, et.al. v. The United States Environmental Protection Agency. et. al. Case No: 82-3214. August 1, 1983 (Box 4)
  - William F. Murphy v. Int'l Union of Operation Engineers, et. al. Case No: 82-3702/3747 (Box 4)
  - Roy Wilson v. Barry Mintzes. Case No: 83-1046. January 18, 1984 (Box 4)
  - Richard Runyan v. NCR Corp. Case No. 83-3862. Original Hearing Date: October 12, 1984; En Blanc Hearing Date: December 16, 1985 (Box 4)
  - Luther D. Mullen & Richard G. Shepherd v. Secretary of HHS. Case No: 84-1455/84-5352. December 16, 1985 (Box 5)
  - Richard A. Newman v. Grand Trunk Western Railroad Co. Case No. 84-1535. September 19, 1985 (Box 5)
  - U.S. v. Gene A. Blanton. Case No: 83-5319. January 24, 1984 (Box 5)
  - Eric Weir v. George Wilson, Dept. of Corrections, et. al. Case No: 83-5592. June 12, 1984 (Box 5)
  - In the Matter of: Timothy R. Pearson and Mary T. Pearson. Case No. 84-1045. January 10, 1985 (Box 5)
  - U.S. v. Marlon Louis Johnson, et. al. Case No: 84-1488. August 24, 1984 (Box 5)
  - Walter A. Walker v. Consumers Power Co. Case No. 84-1653. March 7, 1986 (Box 5)
  - John Sinclair, et. al. v. Kenneth Schriber, et. al. Case No. 84-1669. October 6, 1986 (Box 5)
  - U.S. v. Ronald Ebens, Case No: 84-1757. December 12, 1985 (Box 5)
  - Pinney Dock and Transport Co., et. al. v. Penn Central Corp.; et.al. Case No: 84-3653/3654/3876/3877. October 29, 1985, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Frederick C. Simpson v. Midland-Ross Corp. Case No. 85-1381/85-1676. August 14, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Dorothy Ledesma, et. al. v. John Block, et. al. Case No. 85-1730. August 5, 1986 (Box 5)
  - In Re: Benedectin Litigation. Case No: 85-3858/3876/3877, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Affolder, Inc. v. Preston Carroll Company, et. al. Case No. 86-5348/5349. March 12, 1987 (Box 5)
  - William Dougherty v. Parsec, Inc. et. al. Case No. 86-3482. April 27, 1987 (Box 5)
  - Penney, et. al. v. Kennedy, et. al. & Lovvorn, et. al. v. City of Chattanooga, et. al. Case No. 86-6280/6281. December 7, 1988 (Box 6)
  - Donnie Moore v. Al Parke, Warden, et. al. Case No: 87-5690. March 3, 1988 (Box 6)
  - 88-1863. Correspondence (Box 6)
  - James Tierney, et. al. v. City of Toledo, et. al. Case No: 88-4047. August 11, 1989 (Box 6)
  - U.S. v. James Richard Burton. Case No. 88-5508. April 20, 1989 (Box 6)
  - U.S. & State of Michigan, et. al. v. AKZO Coating of America, et. al. Case No: 89-2092/2137. October 1, 1990 (Box 6)
  - Chance Cordrey, et. al. v. R. J. Euckert, et. al. Case No. 89-3035. (Box 6)
  - Lorna Cassady v. Thurman Tackett. Case No. 89-5679. April 30, 1990 (Box 6)
  - Dr. Paul Maguire, et. al. v. Robert C. Thompson, et. al. Case No. 90-3505. September 26, 1991 (Box 6)
  - Emmett R. Davis, et. al. v. The Mutual Life Insurance Co. of NY (MONY), et. al. Case No. 90-3560/3561/3587/3878/3879/3881, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Ronald Grossheim, et. al. v. Freight Liner Corp. Case No. 91-1255. November 18, 1991 (Box 6)
  - In Re: Air Crash Disaster at Detroit Metropolitan Airport on August 16, 1987. Case No. 91-2328/92-1776-1787 August 13, 1993, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Not labeled (Box 7)
  - United States v. Walter Leroy Moody, Jr. Case No. 95-8972/8815/6857/8571/8722/96-1054/1055/1069/8348, 10 folders (Box 7)
  - U.S. v. Manuel Hernandez (98-1239)(98-2298) & U.S. v. Oscar Solis (99-1616). September 26, 2000, 2 folders (Box 7)
- U.S. Court Of Appeals Case Files (other noteworthy cases)
  - 75-1646. CBS, Inc. v. Hon. Don J. Young (Re: Kent State) (Box 11)
  - 75-1801 etc.
    - Ford Motor Co. v. USA and ICC (Box 11)
    - General Motors Co. v. USA and ICC (Box 11)
    - American Motors Corp. v. USA and ICC (Box 11)
    - Chrysler Corp. v. USA and ICC (Box 11)
  - 75-2121. U.S. v. One 1975 Mercury (En Banc case Re: Hoffa) (Box 11)
  - 75-2518. Andretta v. USA (Re: Hoffa) (Box 11)
  - 76-2468. James Earl Ray v. J.H. Rose, Warden (Box 11)
  - 76-2632. James Earl Ray v. Time, Inc., et al. (Box 11)
  - 77-5074. U.S. v. Anthony Giacalone (Re: Hoffa) (Engel was member of the panel) (Box 11)
  - Re: Northern District of Ohio Chief Judge Frank Battisti (Box 11)
  - Re: Northern District of Ohio Chief Judge Frank Battisti (Box 12)
- U.S. District Court For The Western District Of Michigan Case Files
  - M-56-72-CA, Wisconsin Potawatomies v. Houston (Box 8)
  - CA-1300. Soo Line v. Hocking Construction (Box 8)
  - CA-1394. Heikkila v. Evansville (Box 8)
  - CA-1358. Northern Automatic v. Mercer Alloy (Box 8)
  - CA-5691. Groh v. Decker (Box 8)
  - CA-1279. Bosch Brewing Co. v. Pabst Brewing Co. (Box 8)
- U.S. District Court For The Western District Of Michigan Case Files (noteworthy cases)
  - G-287-72-CA. Americans United for Separation of Church and State, et al. v. Porter, et al. (Box 13)
  - CA-6386. Higgins, et al. v. Board of Education City of Grand Rapids, MI, et al. (Grand Rapids school desegregation case) (Box 14)
  - CA-6386. Higgins, et al. v. Board of Education City of Grand Rapids, MI, et al. (Grand Rapids school desegregation case) (Box 15)
- Three Judge U.S. District Court Cases
  - 74-70164. Mercer v. Michigan State Bd. of Ed. (Box 8)
  - 5-71429. First Federal Sav. & Loan v. Mich. Municipal Finance (Box 8)
  - G76-164 CA. McCarthy v. Secy. of State of Michigan (Box 8)
- Sixth Circuit Court Of Appeals Three Judge Administrative Cases
  - 71-2031. Hodgson v. Elm Hill Meats (Box 8)
  - 71-1789. Robin Products v. Tomecek (Box 8)
  - 71-1644. Cascade Corp. v. NLRB (Box 8)
  - 71-2081. Willyerd v. Buildex Co. (Box 8)
  - 74-1410. Thermtron Products v. Hon. H. David Hermansdorfer (Box 8)
  - 75-2249. First Natl. Bank of Salem v. Hirsch (Box 8)
  - 76-1444. Holmes v. U.S. Dist. Ct. (Box 9)
  - 77-5276. USA v. Taylor (Box 9)
  - 78-3223. City of Cleveland v. Cleveland Electric Illuminating Co. (Box 9)
- Alphabetical Files
  - American Bar Foundation (Box 9)
  - AO-Article III Judge's Division (Box 9)
  - B-Miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Bill of Rights Dedication (Box 9)
  - C-Miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Cincinnati-Court of Appeals (Box 9)
  - D, E-Miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Engel Biographical Materials (Box 9)
  - Engel, Albert J., 2 folders (Box 9)
  - F-Miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Federal Judicial Center (Box 9)
  - Federal Bar Association Newsletter (Box 9)
  - Gibson, Judge (Box 9)
  - Griffin, Robert P. (Box 9)
  - H-Miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Intercircuit Assignment-11th Circuit (Box 9)
  - Intercircuit Conflicts (Box 9)
  - IOLTA Programs (Box 9)
  - J, K, L-Miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Lansing Courthouse Dedication (Box 9)
  - Michigan, University of (Box 9)
  - Michigan, University of-Committee of Visitors (Box 9)
  - Miles, Judge (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - McCree, Wade H., Jr. (Box 9)
  - Opinions Published (Box 9)
  - Opinions Published-District Court (Box 9)
  - P-Miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Panel Reports & Opinions of 6th Circuit (Box 9)
  - Parole Commission (Box 9)
  - R-Miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Restructuring the Judicial Council (Box 9)
  - Ripple, Hon. Kenneth F. (Box 9)
  - Rules Committee (Box 9)
  - S-Miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Sentencing Guidelines (Box 9)
  - Sixth Circuit (Box 9)
  - Sixth Circuit Practitioner's Handbook (Box 9)
  - T-Miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Tenth Appeals Judge (Box 9)
  - Third Judge-W.D. Mich. (Box 9)
  - Vacancy/Successor (Box 9)
  - W-Miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Weddings (Box 9)
  - Weighting of Appeals Study (Box 9)
  - West Publishing Co. (Box 9)
  - X Y Z-Miscellaneous (Box 9)
- Chief Judge Files
  - 1989 U.S. Judicial Conference (Box 10)
  - Advisory Committee on Rules (Box 10)
  - American Newspaper Editors Assoc. May 17, 1989 (Box 10)
  - Judicial Resources Committee (Box 10)
  - Committee to Review Sixth Circuit Conference (Box 10)
  - Death Penalty Panels (Box 10)
  - State-Federal Meetings (Box 10)
  - Court Meeting 02/08/1989 (Box 10)
  - Court Meeting 05/10/1989 (Box 10)
  - Council Meetings (Box 10)
  - Court Security (Box 10)
  - Juries-Sixth Circuit Committee (Pattern Jury Instructions) (Box 10)
  - Rules Committee 1988 (Box 10)
  - Federal Judicial Center (Box 10)
  - Statistical Analysis & Reports Division (Box 10)
  - Chief Judge-Notes/Business (Box 10)
  - United States Judicial Conference 1988 (Box 10)
  - Retreat-The Homestead 1989 (Box 10)
  - Engel, Albert J.-Senior Judge (Box 10)
  - Chief Judge Matters-Judge Merritt (Box 10)
  - Albert J. Engel-Chief Judge (Box 10)
  - Circuit Matters (Box 10)
  - Biennial Survey (Box 10)
  - Continuing Legal Education for Michigan Judges (Box 10)
  - Dormant Commerce Clause Program (Box 10)
  - Toledo Law Review (Box 10)
- Other Administrative Court Records
  - Council Meeting files (Box 10)
  - Conference files
    - Judicial Conference 1979 (Box 10)
  - Rules Committee (Box 10)
  - Other Committees
    - Committee on Circuit Conference (Box 10)
    - Committee on Pattern Jury Instruction (Box 10)
    - Docket Control Committees (Box 10)
  - Court Meeting Files
    - Court Retreats (Box 10)
    - Court Meetings (Box 10)
    - Judicial Center Seminar (Box 10)
    - Appelate Judges Seminar 1980 (Box 10)
    - Ohio Bar Assoc. Speech 1994 (Box 10)
- Personal / Biographical
  - Memoirs of Albert J. Engel, Jr., 2 volumes (Box 16)
    (the memoirs were written following his retirement from the bench)
  - Letters written from overseas while serving in the military during World War II 1944-1946, photocopies in 1 binder (Box 16)